なんば　むった
ひびと
＜日々人が…帰ってくる＞
Hibito is coming home.
きかん
いのちづな
＜地球に帰還する時の命綱となる
パラシュートを手がけたのは➡
The parachute which will safely bring him back was designed by Pico Norton,
ピコ･ノートン｡
私達が訓練として参加した➡
our team advisor during the Comeback Competition portion of our training.
｢カムバックコンペティション｣の
サポート役だ＞
The astronauts will once again be using Orion for their reentry,
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)
今回の飛行士達は ３年前の
パラシュｰト事故の時と同じく➡
the module that suffered a parachute accident three years ago.
帰還船オリオンで
地球に帰ってきます｡➡
This will be the first reentry for a lunar mission since the accident,
今回が 事故以来 初めての
月からの帰還ということで➡
and many involved are getting nervous.
関係者の間にも緊張が…｡
(ピコ)クソがっ！➡
Damn it.
They're using Brian's accident to build hype!
ブライアン達の事故を
あお
くだらねえ煽りに使いやがって！
The lives of the three returning astronauts are in your hands.
(ビンス)帰ってくる あの３人の
命を背負わされてるんだ｡
I presume that it's at the point where pressure has become fear, Pico.
その重圧が恐怖に
変わっている頃だろう ピコ｡➡
君が仕込んだパラシュートが➡
It comes down to whether the parachute you designed will properly deploy.
ちゃんと開くかどうかに
かかっている｡
ハァ…➡
俺がやったんだ｡
開くに決まってんだろ｡
I designed it.
It'll open.
＜コンペ本番➡
In the Comeback Competition, Pieco, our rover, placed fifth out of fifteen.
ピエコ
私達がＰＩＥＣＯと名付けた
ローバーは １５組中５位＞
Among the AsCans, we came in second.
＜アスキャンチームの中では
２位となった＞
Guess it's goodbye to this room.
(ケンジ)この部屋とも お別れか｡
だな｡
Yep.
(せりか)どうします？ＰＩＥＣＯ｡
What should we do with Pieco?
There's only one place
こいつの行き先は…➡
もう決まってるんじゃない？
for this girl to go.
SPACE BROTHERS
You've always been in my heart
But you don't say a thing or even smile
We've always been together
We're ignorant, but we believe
All the time I spent with you
Felt like a dream
We connected the stars and drew pictures
To our hearts' content
Let our hearts, shivering in excitement,
Use the sky as a canvas
And merge to form an everlasting image
#61 Those Who Wait for Hibito
Everything's green, with all the bushes and trees.
[TV](ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)芝と木のある風景に
飢えてるよ｡➡
帰ったら息子のアランと
公園で遊びたいね｡リンダは？
I can't wait to go home and play with my son, Alan.
What about you, Linda?
[TV](ﾘﾝﾀﾞ)私は 家族との
バーベキューが楽しみ｡➡
I'm looking forward to a family barbecue.
あと ひとりでミュージカル
見に行きたいな｡
And I'd like to go catch a musical.
And you, Hibito?
(ｸﾗｳﾄﾞ)ヒビトは どうだ？
[TV](南波日々人)
ん～俺は やっぱり➡
I'm planning on taking my bike for a ride.
愛用のチャリンコに乗って
どっか行くだろうね｡
好きだな 自転車｡
You love that bike of yours, huh?
Well, it's probably covered in dust.
ま 相当
ホコリかぶってるだろうけど｡
かね
あずま
(吾妻)聞こえてるか 日々人｡
Can you hear this bell ringing,
鐘の音｡
Hibito?
聞こえてますよ｡
ありがとう 吾妻さん｡
I can hear it.
Thank you, Azuma.
I'll see you back on Earth,
地球で また会おう 日々人｡
Hibito.
(バディ)ダミア～ン リンダ～
ヒビトォ～！➡
Damian! Linda!
Hibito!
さびしくなるぜ チクショー｡
It'll be lonely without you guys...
Search and rescue team,
サーチ＆レスキューチーム！
いつまで雑談してる｡
enough chatter.
出番が先でも 今 集中しろ｡
これも打ち上げだぞ｡
You aren't on call right now, but you should stay focused.
We're still in the middle of a launch.
ヒビトの心拍数が
上昇してますが…｡
Hibito's heart rate is rising.
本人に伝える必要はない！
予定通り 打ち上げてやろう｡
He doesn't need that information.
Continue with the launch.
帰還船オリオンの位置データを
着陸船アルタイルに送信！
Transmitting reentry module Orion's current coordinates to landing craft Altair.
(管制官)オリオン 位置を
アルタイルでも照合！
Altair has confirmed Orion's coordinates.
Fuel, oxygen, power, launch speed confirmed.
(管制官)燃料 空気 電力
打ち上げ速度を確認！
All right, begin the final countdown.
よし 最終カウントダウン開始！
(管制官)１０…９…８…７…６…｡
10.
9.
8.
7.
6.
Okay, let's go home.
さあ…帰ろう｡
(管制官)５…４…３…２…１…➡
5.
4.
3.
2.
1.
リフトオフ！
Liftoff.
We have liftoff.
(管制官)打ち上げ成功！
高度５００メートル！
Current altitude, 500 meters.
ハァ…｡
《ありがと…》
Thanks.
《また来るよ ブライアン》
I'll be back, Brian.
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)
今 月軌道上には 地球への
帰還船が３機 回っています｡➡
Currently, three reentry modules are in orbit around the moon.
セス
ＣＥＳ－５１クルーが
乗って行ったオリオンと➡
Orion, carrying the CES-51 members,
ロシアチームのルーニエ２号｡➡
the Russian Luniere 2,
and a reserve three-person Orion, sent unmanned in 2025 to the moon.
もうひとつは
予備として２０２５年に➡
無人で月に送られた
３人乗りのオリオンです｡➡
現在 クルーが乗っている
アルタイルは➡
The crew is currently on board Altair, which will shortly dock with Orion.
１時間後にオリオンとドッキング｡
のち
クルーがオリオンに移った後➡
Once the crew is on board Orion, Altair will be released.
アルタイルを切り離します｡
切り離し完了後…｡
Once that has happened...
あ～あ
いらね～っつってんのに…｡
I told them it wasn't necessary...
ピエコは あんたが預かってくれ｡
You hold onto Pieco for us.
心淋しいが…｡
It's hard to give her up, though...
Then why not keep it yourselves?
だったら
自分で持っときゃいいだろ｡
Well, you know...
こいつは あれだ…
血と汗と涙と…➡
We put a lot of blood, sweat, and tears into this girl.
そんなものを流しながら
作った作品だ！
いつ血が出たんだ？
When did you bleed?
僕らのことを忘れないために
もらってください｡
Please accept this as something to remember us by.
そういうこった｡
Here you go.
おぼ
しっかり憶えといてくれよ
俺らの顔を｡
Don't forget our faces.
いずれ
あんたの手がけた帰還船で➡
Because we're going to become astronauts who return to Earth on one of your spaceships.
地球に帰ってくる
宇宙飛行士だからな｡
現在
フンッ 言ってくれんじゃね～か
あいつら…｡
Those guys sure talk big...
⦅命を預かる技術者の気持ちを
知れと言うなら➡
Since you want us to know how it feels to be an engineer responsible for our lives,
あんたは 命をかける側の
気持ちを知ってくれ⦆
we'd like you to know how it feels to be out there, risking them.
《ってか はははは…
確かに その通りだ｡➡
Heh...
He's absolutely right.
俺だったら恐え～わ｡俺みたいに
ビビってる奴に命を託すの》
I'd be too scared to entrust my life to a coward like myself.
Some mineral water here.
マスター
ミネラルウォーターくれ｡
あいよ！
Got it.
《心配は いらねえ｡➡
Don't worry...
ヒビト達も お前らも
かえ
俺が無事に還してやる｡➡
I'll bring Hibito and the rest of you home safely.
That's my job.
それが 俺の仕事だ》
アポちゃ～ん！久しぶり～！➡
Apo! It's been forever!
あ～！かわい～わね～！
日本で見てもアメリカで見ても！
You're adorable whether in Japan or in America...
Ugly.
(南波父)ぶちゃいく｡
ビーフジャーキー！➡
Beef jerky!
大きい男になるんだぞ｡
Grow up to be a big boy.
大きい男になるよぉ！
You'll be a big boy!
You can tell he's my son.
さすが俺の子だ｡
(母)おみやげ いっぱい
持って来たわよ～！➡
I brought plenty of Japanese gifts, Mu.
にっぽん
ムッちゃん 日本的なやつ！
ホラッ もずくでしょ～
ふえるワカメでしょ➡
Look!
We have mozuku seaweed,
fueru wakame kelp,
鳩サブローでしょ～｡
うどんも大量に持って来たぞ｡
and hato saburo cookies.
We brought lots of udon, too.
ちょっと２人とも！
おみやげは後でい～から！
Come on, guys!
You can show me what you brought later.
We should be watching NASA TV.
ナサテレビ
早くＮＡＳＡＴＶ見ろよ！
今から日々人がドッキングだぞ！
He's docking now.
(父)日々人が…
何とドッキングするんだ？
What's Hibito docking with?
あ いや…日々人はしね～けど…｡
I didn't mean that Hibito would do the docking.
《めんどくせ～！》
This is such a pain...
Reentry module Orion is within 100 meters.
[TV](管制官)
着陸船オリオン
距離１００ｍまで接近｡➡
Initiate docking sequence.
ドッキングシークエンス開始｡
アプローチ…｡
Begin approach.
ドキ…ドキ…｡
口で言うな｡
Ba-dum, ba-dum!
Don't say that out loud.
[TV](管制官)ドッキング成功｡
Docking successful.
(母)やった～！
日々人～ バンザーイ！
っし！
Yay!
Hurray for Hibito!
うむ｡ドッキドキの
ドッキングだったな｡
ホント！
That was a shocking docking.
Really!
I'm glad I said a little prayer.
がん
《願掛けといて良かったぜ》
《なんかもう…
捨てられね～な コイツ…》
I don't think I can throw this thing away now...
《こんなもんが…》
This little toy.
どうしよう お父さん｡六太が
人形を じっと見つめてんのよ｡
Oh no, dear...
Mutta's staring at a doll.
I'm getting worried.
なんか恐いわ｡
心配するな｡
There's no need for worry.
I went through that, too.
私にも そ～いう時期はあった｡
The three astronauts have begun the final check before their return.
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)
３名の宇宙飛行士は帰還する為の
最終ﾁｪｯｸに入っている模様です｡
《はぁ～あ…もうすぐ
帰ってくんだなぁ 日々人…》
Hibito will be back soon.
Amazing!
ヤバ～い！
キャ～！
《日本では今 日本人初の
月面からの帰還ということで➡
In Japan, there's a huge Hibito boom in anticipation of the first Japanese person on the moon's return.
恐ろしいほどの日々人ブームが
巻き起こっている》
《奴の帰国後のスケジュールは
パレード 講演会に➡
Once he's back in Japan, his schedule will be filled with parades, speeches,
テレビ出演の予定で
すでに いっぱいだ》
and TV appearances.
He'll be even more popular than he already is...
《さらにモテるんだろうな…》
《帰って来なきゃいいのに…
俺が宇宙行くまで》
I wish he wouldn't get back until I'd made it to space.
ワン…｡
I guess this means nothing's changed.
《結局 相変わらず
私という男は…》
《弟の先を行くわけでもなく
帰ってくる弟に➡
I'm still not leading the way for my brother,
and I don't know what to do for him when he returns.
何かしてやれることもない｡➡
じまん
自慢の弟を自慢するだけ
みじめになる》
The more I think about it, the worse I feel.
ほら｡
There.
でおく
《出遅れた兄だ》
I've just fallen behind...
It won't be long
《もうすぐ…
日々人が帰ってくる》
before Hibito returns.
Hey, Mu!
(母)≪ちょっとムッちゃん！
早く遊びに行こうよ～｡➡
Let's go out.
せっかくの休みなのに～≫
We're supposed to be on vacation.
もうちょっと待ってくれよ｡
Just give me a minute.
それ 日々人の自転車？
なんで みがいてんの？
Is that Hibito's bicycle?
Why are you polishing it?
Why?
なんでって…｡
う～ん…まあ…｡
Well...
な～んとなくだな｡
I just felt like it.
(ピコ息子)ヘヘッ！アハハ！
パパがカッコつけてるよ！
変だよ！
Mommy!
Daddy's getting dressed up!
It's weird!
さわ
(ピコ)そう騒ぐな｡➡
Don't make such a fuss.
I only look slightly better than normal.
いつもより ちょっと
カッコよくなっただけだろ｡
なんでネクタイしてんの パパ？
なんで？
気持ちわる～｡
Why are you wearing a tie, Daddy?
Why?
That's dumb.
ネクタイを締める理由なんてのは
１個しかねえ｡
There's only one reason to tighten a tie.
仕事が 無事に終わった後に
ゆるめるためだ｡
To have something to loosen when your job's done.
へえ～ 気持ちわる｡
That's dumb.
《必ず 成功する》
This is going to be a success.
行ってくる｡
I'm off.
(子供たち)行ってらっしゃ～い｡
Bye!
(案内担当官)アスキャンの皆さん
次は こちらへ｡➡
AsCans, please come over here.
きどう
ここは フライト軌道担当官の
ブースだ｡➡
This is the Flight Dynamics Officer's desk.
いじょう
フライト経路に異状があった場合
軌道修正を提案する｡➡
If any issues with the flight path arise, he'll determine a new course.
次はフライトサージャンを
紹介しよう｡➡
Next, I'll introduce the Flight Surgeons.
宇宙飛行士の健康管理を
担当している｡➡
They manage the astronauts' health as long as they're in space.
今回の担当は この２人だ｡
サイモンとオリビア｡
For this mission, we have Simon and Olivia.
(サイモン)はじめまして｡
(オリビア)よろしく｡
Nice to meet you.
It's a pleasure.
《なんとっ
こんなところにも美人が…》
What's this? Another beautiful lady?
(案内担当官)次は こっちへ｡
Next, we'll move this way.
(ジェニファー)《あのムッタが➡
I never thought
本当に管制室に入る日が
来るとはね…》
I'd see Mutta inside Mission Control...
But, but... Mutta told me!
でもねっ でもねっ 六太がね➡
しんかんせん
帰還船は新幹線の120倍の
スピードで帰ってくるって➡
The reentry modules return at 120 times the speed of a bullet train...
言うのよ｡もう 私 訳わかんなくて
なんか怖いわ｡
I'm so confused, I'm terrified!
(小町)大丈夫 大丈夫！➡
It'll be fine...
な～んも心配あらへんよ お母さん
私らから見てたら➡
You don't need to worry about a thing, ma'am.
To us, it looks like they're crashing.
｢落ちてくる～！｣っちゅう
感じやけど➡
日々人君達からしたら 玄関の
ドア開けて入ってくるくらいの➡
But for Hibito and the rest, it's as natural as walking in the front door.
もんやがな｡｢ただいま～｣言うて｡
Like, "I'm home, honey!"
Oh, really?
は～ ほんまでっか｡
ほんま ほんま｡笑って待っとこ｡
You bet... Just keep smiling while you wait.
お前が腕時計までするとは
ずいぶんキメてきなぁ ピコ｡
Pico, if you're wearing a watch, you must have really dressed up.
ふんっ｡
ゆうしゃ
帰還ってのは勇者を称え➡
The return is a ceremony to hail the heroes.
むか
おごそ
迎え入れる 厳かな式典だ｡➡
せいだい
打ち上げの盛大なショーとは違う｡
It's different from the show during launch.
まあ 厳かなのは パラシュートが
開くまでの話だけどな｡
Well, the atmosphere lightens once the parachute opens...
Orion, this is Houston.
オリオン こちらヒューストン｡➡
大気圏突入は ３５分後｡➡
In thirty-five minutes, you'll be entering the atmosphere.
Correct your angle of entry at 140 kilometers, and detach the service module.
高度１４０キロで
突入角度を修正し➡
サービスモジュールを切り離す｡
[TV]了解｡
Roger that.
《い いよいよか》
I-It's finally time.
《管制室だけでも
これだけの人間が…》
All of the people in Mission Control
《この帰還の 一員となる》
are a part
of this return.
And for Pico,
《ピコにとっても この帰還は…》
this return is...
Reentry angle has been corrected.
再突入角度 修正完了｡
Detaching service module.
ぶんり
サービスモジュール 分離！
Service module has been detached from propulsion module.
サービスモジュールと
すいしん
推進モジュールの分離 完了！
(管制官)地上側でも分離を確認｡
Confirm that detachment is complete.
ハァ～…｡
しせいせいぎょ
(管制官)最終姿勢制御｡
Final altitude check.
たいきけん
(管制官)大気圏 突入開始！
Entering atmosphere.
がいへき
(管制官)外壁温度上昇！
Hull temperature rising.
(管制官)予定高度を通過｡
ごさ
(管制官)機体角度の誤差が発生中｡
Reentry altitude broken.
Possible error in reentry angle.
(管制官)機体の位置データの
だんぞくてき
ﾓﾆﾀﾘﾝｸﾞに 断続的な➡
Possible issue with the sensors monitoring the spacecraft's position.
不具合が見られる｡
(管制官)体温 正常値を確認｡
Confirm that hull temperature is...
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)帰還船オリオンが
再突入しました｡➡
Reentry module Orion has entered the atmosphere.
３年前の事故と同じ方法ですが…｡
They will use the same method of entry as three years ago.
らっか
落下ポイント予測 修正中｡
Recalculating anticipated landing coordinates.
(管制官)３人の心拍数が
最大値を…｡
Heart rates for all three have peaked.
かねつ
(管制官)機体 最大加熱！
Hull temperature peaking!
とうたつ
高度２万５千フィートに到達！
メインパラシュートを開く｡
Altitude, 25,000 feet.
Main parachutes deployed.
(管制官)電力値の通信が…｡
Electronic transmissions are...
(管制官)パラシュート 展開成功！
Parachutes successfully deployed!
Heat shield ejected.
たいねつ
(管制官)耐熱シールド放出！
かどう
エアバッグ 正常稼動！
Airbags functioning normally.
(管制官)オリオン 無事着陸！➡
Orion has made a safe landing!
サーチ＆レスキュー 急行せよ！
Dispatch search and rescue!
おかえり～ 日々人～！
Welcome back, Hibito!
All three are okay!
≪３人とも無事だ！≫
あ～ 土のにおいだ｡
I can smell the dirt...
風もいいね｡
And the wind feels good.
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ･ｸｳｪﾗｰ｡ﾘﾝﾀﾞ･ｸﾘﾌ｡
ﾅﾝﾊﾞ･ﾋﾋﾞﾄ｡➡
Damian Kweller, Linda Cliff, and Nanba Hibito
ただ今 ヒューストンに到着です！
have just arrived in Houston.
Hibito!
日々人～！キャ～！
よう 日々人｡おけ～り｡
Yo, Hibito.
Welcome back.
た～いま｡
Good to be back.
As you place your hopes on the distant moon
And leave on your journey
You smile in spite of your loneliness
Because you believe in yourself
It doesn't matter if your wings don't match
Spread them out
As you
begin your long journey (try now) (try now)
I'm sure you can make it
Please don't hesitate
to move straight forward
You took
all your pain and sorrow (no more) (no more)
And turned it into your strength
So I'm sure even your destiny to fight many a battle
Is on your side
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#62 Those Who Dream Far
Shortly after Hibito's return, Amanti has a revelation for me.
＜日々人の帰還から 間もなく
私は アマンティに呼び出される＞
I saw you looking pained
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)＜私が見たのは ムッタが
とても悲しんで➡
and very sad.
つら
辛
い思いをしている姿＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Those Who Dream Far"
はし
まえ
走り出せ前向いて
そら
かじかむ手で空に描いた
きみ
みらい
しゅくふく
あか
君の未来に祝福の灯りともす
ひら
切り開け
その手で
こえ
聞こえてるかい？
この声が